[Music]
or something like that do you think
that's a mostly adequate word translated
or do you think there's something more
appropriate that kind of describes the
pali word Samadhi
the well there's nothing wrong with with
a term concentration in itself but the
problem today is due to many popular
popular popularize meditation techniques
and the contemporary take on the whole
meditation practice usually
concentration and misrepresenting what
was meant by Samadhi and certainly
prevents people from from correctly
doing it very often so the better word
for Samadhi would be composure because
the whole the whole notion of Samadhi
Samadhi in itself means keeping things
together binding together
yeah you can say concentration means you
bring something together but it's it's
it's it has much more narrower
connotations than if you say composure
something that you have to compose and
then maintain maintain that composition
that that takes
takes different type of effort than the
effort of focusing an effort of
concentration so and also concentration
can can kind of indicate for people you
concentrate of something so you switch
everything else out but it's more like
you compose yourself above everything
else altogether
so then nothing can bother you in that
sense not because you shut it all out
but because you come beyond it so when
people usually from a commentarial point
of view talk about Samadhi it generally
brings up this idea of a meditation
object the city manga for example this
forty so-called
objects ranging from sceners to various
recollections of the triple gem so on
and so forth that one becomes absorbed
in and focuses on as much as possible
you know the common technique is a
you lose your focus and then you bring
yourself back to the meditation object
is there is there any validity in that
practice or are you saying that it's
gonna it's it's it's a completely wrong
direction to go to go by if you want to
develop your mind if you want to
practice concentration in a sense of
concentration that's fine but the type
of composure that the buddha was
encouraging and talking about is the one
that's it's founded upon mindfulness and
usually if people do concentration
practice some other practice in terms of
focusing it requires you to focus on the
particular as in the object of your
meditation and you keep trying to
observe it as closely as possible and
that will inevitably have to that
inevitable has to result in in losing
the sight of the general awareness in
regard to what you were doing which is
focusing on a particular object so what
I'm saying is that if you chase in the
object you cannot be mindful of doing
that while if you start looking at the
nature of object the background of the
reason particular experience you are
actually playing along the the basis of
mindfulness that the Buddha did say you
can't have too much of and it's a good
thing to develop
so it seems the most like the opposite
of absorption
yeah I mean again you can say absorption
but it's not a job from the one point
the chats everything else out its
absorption in the more general point
that includes everything else in that's
why the Buddha gave such similes like
like a gatekeeper or or a man who is too
old too who needs to look after the
children but he's too old to change them
but he's too old to change them
individually if he chases one child he
loses the sight of all the other
children in the yard so what you do you
find a place from which you can see them
all at the same time not to the same
extent but at the same time
in the same sense that the gatekeeper
would know he wouldn't chase people who
come through the gate into the into the
fenced off area because she knows I
don't need to chase them I know that
they're inside and that's all I need to
know that's why that's why any practice
of mindfulness to the results in the
correct practice of composure the Buddha
would say he knows there is a pleasant
feeling present present feeling pleasant
feeling present as pleasant so you know
there is a pleasant feel for oh there is
an urn unpleasant feeling there is a
neutral field oh there is a depressed
mind present or there is a latent mind
present all of that results in
incomplete fulfillment of the
satipatthana which results in
fulfillment of Samadhi as well so it's
quite the opposite then if you were to
say oh there is a related mind present
in regard to this experience or that
experience or why is it elated because
of this is related and what what it what
it does result in and what is it bring
to be and so on it's actually you stop
being concerned with a particular
content and you just look at the general
nature of it and that's the beginning of
Samadhi so whether you're sitting
cross-legged whether you're doing
walking meditation whether you're
standing or laying down mindfulness and
Samadhi basically are are inseparable if
done right and they're certainly
mindfulness unwavering mindfulness is
where your Samadhi becomes
so it's not that you must focus on
something else they will then result in
the samadhi and then you go back to
practice your mindfulness mindfulness
when developed that's what Samadhi is
and that's why we're that kind of
general knowledge of the nature thing of
the nature that is present in regard to
any particular thing that's exactly how
you develop it personal that's why
certain summit my persona go hand in
hand you cannot possibly separate by
having the correct summit that correct
in correct calmness in regard to that
composure means the clarity of the
nature of things is present because
you're not absorbed you're not pulled by
the content so you so your insight in
regard to that nature is being developed
through that summer term and an equally
if you if you focus on the insight of
the nature of the things well in order
well knowing and discerning that nature
means you are composing the right
mindfulness right there and then so
again then Samadhi in your some other
gets developed really personal in the
correct sense of that word
quickly there's also this idea given of
like so-called stages or steps of some
money the commentaries mention things like
the commentaries mention things like
that excess concentration preceding
jhana momentary concentration so we don't have
momentary concentration so we don't have
to go into those to the plate as you
want to but in terms of I guess is is
there a way to kind of quantify like
more or less Samadhi or is that kind of
misguided to start measuring to begin
with yeah you can't measure it because
it would require you to step outside of
yourself and somehow magically measure
the extent of your concentration which
is dwelling consumable and then
secondary you never find any of that
stuff in the sutras when the Buddha did
talk about meditation he was always in
well he was he was in very different
terms in the terms that came later with
it with the commentary and a kind of
contemporary Buddhist technique
meditation where you're catching the
moments observing them
trying to trying to sort of get the
right pure perception that will sort of
tell you the truth behind the
appearances and so on all of that I
think we cover that in other talks but
all of that kind of assumes you well not
being aware of yourself to begin with
which means you're not mindful of the
general background and then secondary
also it is all very often founded upon
the external view of yourself as if you
can observe the pure moment for example
that's independent of your experiences
at home that will require you to somehow
step outside of it and that's just
inconceivable it's conceivable only in
the in the form of wrong conception
which is why it's wrong fear
distinguishes we could say between a
wrong samadhi right and samadhi
there's a wrong he's so passionate right
so what is it specifically that makes
one samadhi right it's that it's that
direction that I'm talking about
he feels samadhi is concerned with
composing the nature of things to be
present and in dude in your experience
that's the right model of Samadhi along
the right lines if your composure
concentration is concerned and focusing
on the particular or whatever it's you
from to view them with in further
particular within that particular within
that particular it's you're basically
preying upon something you're hunting
down the moment chasing and catching it
trying to see it in its arising and
that's a completely wrong direction
that's why the Buddha did say get there
comparison like when a person doesn't
doesn't know how to marry they rightly
he miss meditates premeditates under
meditate over meditates so to speak
he cannot meditate and then he says it's
like like like an owl preying upon
waiting for a for a mouse to show its
head so he can grab it so he can catch
it so he can witness it whatever you
want to call it but the attitude is the
same or like a cat catching a man
catching a fish or something like that
so ends up if your meditation ends up
being about trying to perceive things in
that in that sort of
hunting manner like you're trying to
catch it you're trying to I must not
miss I must not blink because the moment
we slip me I must catch every moment as
it arises that's why the Buddha did
compare that same thing to actually an
animal hunting its prey and because of
that he said that person who meditates
like that he meditates with sensuality
why because it's fully based upon the
domain of the senses so that's why that
Samadhi is wrong as I was explaining in
another talk
people often sort of will disagree with
it because well I find it helpful
but first of all unless a person is
already sotapanna
you don't know what true helpfulness is
so nobody's denying the relative benefit
but I'm highlighting the fact that it
can only be a relative benefit in a
sense of it's a circumstantial benefit
the focus in practicing practice can
only have a circumstantial benefit to
one's peace of mind
if one is looking for a long-term
solution needs to go the other direction
direction that includes the nature of
the arisen phenomena the irate nature of
there is an experience which is where
the nature of unwholesome is so become
skilled in saying things in that general
manner seeing the background behind the
particular appearance there is
simultaneously present with it that's
how you develop the understanding of the
nature of whatever is present in
continuity so related to that here's a
suit from the anger
it's called the Sunday suit and the
Buddha is giving these instructions to a
venerable sutta he says meditate like a
thoroughbred horse not like an inferior
horse how does one meditate like an
inferior horse when an interior horse is
tied up to the feeding trowel he
meditates hey hey H a why a for what
reason because when an inferior horse is
tied up to the seating trout he does not
ask himself well will the horse trainer
make me do today
how will I respond right up to the
feeding job he meditates a a in the same
way said that a certain inferior man
having gone to the forest the root of a
tree meant the dwelling of the mind in
this essential passion overcome by
sensual passion does not understand that
it really is the escape from rhythms
fashioned from within this very
essential passion which he has produced
meditating on busy frets is overwhelmed
and same thing for all the other five
Ingram's is
in this way said one is a man who
meditates like an inferior horse yeah
that's exactly exactly what I'll be
saying now that like in the case of a
horse who is not an inferior host he
wouldn't just look at what's right in
front of it which is hey hey he would
think what's implied in this what will
the the the horse trainer make me do
today yeah he brought this hay for me
but that means something what is the
background of this present there is an
experience for me
he's not just concentrating of what he
wants and often that's why often people
approach they have like a they have a
wholesome motivation they have a right
motivation but they end up approaching
meditation just pure sensuality just to
try trying to get rid of the unpleasant
feeling order order possibility from
Pleasant feeling arising just to sheer
sort of replacement with a good feeling
that I can keep on talking ah Jesus
maintain it forever and I'll never
experience any lack of peace or
discomfort but the true peace and
freedom from discomfort comes from
understanding the nature of the nature
of feelings all the feelings not just
replacing one with the other
that's why people would go through like
often two different najin's and
different techniques and different
retreats just trying to rekindle
different novelty a different sort of
scenarios they will they will be able to
replace their unpleasant existential
feelings or their to keep rien tense'
fiying their their focusing practices
and so on which then obviously results
in some other drawbacks so as that
Souter says you actually reflect even in
Samadhi the whole point of it is to see
bigger picture not to be absorbed and
concentrated upon right like right
what's in front of your nose
so generally when the Buddha talks about
Samadhi it always seems to be in the
context of a path like a gradual path
but obviously there's a Noble Eightfold
Path and there's a number of sutras such
as a much Amman nicaya 39 the greater
discourse a support that gives like a
gradual training that starts with things
like purifying one's conduct leads one
all the way to you know final Nirvana
meetings through the hindrances of
jhanas so I won't read the whole suit
but just generally give the outline it
starts with telling one to develop shame
and fear of wrongdoing to restrain one's
bodily conduct restrain one's verbal
conduct restrain one's mental conduct
practice restraint in the senses
moderation eating wakefulness
mindfulness and full awareness to see
all of those things so I can just
interject it is what prepping you for
becoming more accustomed to dealing and
seeing the background because a non
restrained person is the person who goes
with a with a particular content of
their experience which is a definition
of sensuality and so even if you become
restrained before and your views are
still pertaining to the sensual domain
which is how people often end up and
expecting to perceive the right moment
and the moment of meditation and so on
so that's why all of this is a is a
necessary prerequisite because just by
engaging in restraint mindfulness
wakefulness a verbal restraint mental
restraint as well you are actually
stepping back into that more general
picture and refusing to be pulled and
fully absorbed by the content and then
Samadhi should just be the extension of
that which is why it's a prerequisite
for Samadhi not for something else
but most people end up doing is being
very virtuous very restrained but when
it comes to samadhi they go back into
same type of focusing just a different
object but the attitude of you staring
at the object stays the same even if
that object tries to be a lofty general
background or some some some generic
idea or like a earth element or Cocina
you're doing it in a central manner
through trying to perceive it and focus
on it you're not stepping into it you're
actually trying to absorb yourself into
what you think it is which is why it's
also inseparable from the view if you
think it's a wrong thing means your
meditation will be wrong sorry if you
think it's a thing that actually it
isn't your meditation will be wrong
because you think it wrongly you think
this is this is what Samadhi is this is
what composure is but it isn't and
because of that all of your efforts will
be equally wrong so it sounds like if
you you understand what it means to be
you understand what it means to be
restrained and all these other career
because it's you you do understand yeah
well understanding what it means to be
restrained understanding the place of
restraint toward the beginning of
Samadhi beginning of compulsion that's
what we'll do the same ones that the
skilled monk would establish his mind
and then he said like even even in the
in the first jhana he said whether he he
walks sits down eats urinate
certificates whatever he does it's
divine because she's mind is in such a
lofty established state but you can't do
that if you just focused on one thing
and you forget about yourself entirely
now of course you can get so established
to the point of cessation of perception
and feeling but again that's the
ultimate point that includes everything
else that can ever arise ever has arisen
ever will arise in this world the
ultimate nature of everything is
perception and feeling which is what
determines your experience in the most
general manner of your mind so that's
why whenever they would they would
progress through these different
establishments higher establishments of
the mind in terms of the jhanas and so
on then the infinite space they would
come down to perception feeling it and
oh there is no higher than this
literally that is surmounting the
phenomenological world face in every
shape or form it doesn't matter
so it's it's in a sense of the utmost
general thing it's to be felt and to be
perceived otherwise it doesn't exist
seen when people think about things that
they haven't perceived the felt well
their thoughts are being felt in the sea
which means ultimate if you come to the
root to the experience is the perception
in the feeling which is why the Buddha
said the mind is the forerunner of all
things he determines basically the
direction of your thought and whether
you're going to be aware of the nature
in regard to it or just be focused on
the particular so from there the citta
talks about abandoning the five
entrances their sensuality ill will
toward restlessness remorse
if the Buddha gives various simile is
about that to think he says suppose a
man were to take a loan undertake
business his business were to succeed so
that he could repay all the money of the
old loan and there would remain enough
extra to maintain a wife then on
considering this he would be glad and
full of joy so too when these five
hindrances are a ban on abandoned
himself because seize them respectively
out of debt and so on with the other
assemblies so these these hindrances you
just kind of start by saying just like
what were they what are they hindering
exactly what makes them hinder they
hinder the establishment of the mind on
that general nature of things they sort
of narrow you down they hinder you they
sort of bring you down into that more
particular direction obviously a more of
a hindrance means more offer of a
binding for your mind it is more of that
kind of tunnel vision towards one
particular content you can have we
tweekin hindrances in which case the
mind would still be able to
the hindrances can be weakened as well
in which case that the mind can still be
aware of the general background and
however like a degree of the pool of
those hindrances in terms of degree of
the the clouding so to speak once the
mind is free from hindrances
compatibility once the mind is
completely free from hindrances the mind
can be established upon the general
nature of things without being absorbed
in pulled by the content because that's
the thing that's that's what's in common
to every hindrance it's a certain
contextual pull so to speak you are
pulled by a content as in content of
your doubt sensuality ill-will you can't
just have will will without any
particular object of your real will it's
going to end up being pinned down onto
something so that's that's that's why
that's what all the hindrances have in
common is they're taking you in the
direction of the content they are taking
in the direction of sensuality which is
why they're directly against the proper
Samadhi proper establishment of the mind
so by doing all the things previously
like the restraint and the moderation
and eating or whatnot it is it almost
like strengthening your mind against
increases its yeah it's it's a
preparation it's like people you won't
see a hindrance if you by habitual
you're already well within acting within
the contextual Pope if you're cool by
the content and then you had no
restraint you had no no self-reflection
it's you not aware of the hindrance
where you is just you in the content so
you have to stop exercising behavior
that's already bound with the content of
your senses which is the sense restraint
once you do that then the general nature
of that pull of a hindrance that's when
it becomes revealed and that's why
usually people would give in to the
content it's because bearing that pool
of that hindrance is unpleasant and they
don't know any other way of overcoming
it so the only other ways to forget
about it through giving in to the
content
then having abandoned the hindrances the
Buddha talks about going into the sword
jhanas than having the three true
knowledge 'as the knowledge and past
life knowledge of
being born passing away and knowledge
who said one becoming an Arg on the
basis of that
is planning to ask more about like
Johnna in general in a later video but
with regards to this gradual path it
doesn't sound like it's like a linear
thing so to speak in terms of like you
get Cielo to name D 5% then you progress
to its it's a perpendicular thing so in
that sense you can say linear but not
linear in a sense that you can observe
the line so it's perpendicular because
well it goes right through your being
right through your point of view
that's what establishment of mine is
that's why developing the general
background that sort of transcends your
limited point of view that you have
cultivated through engagement with the
senses so in that sense yeah there is a
certain gradual development but it's not
linear exactly like on I'll do one then
I did two then I did three then I do
four five six seven
that's all off to say it's not a
mechanical method which is usually how
many people would like to approach their
meditation just tell me what to do and
what to look for so I don't have to
think about anything
there's another elicitation of a less
less broad but still I guess gradual
comes up in a few different places but
this one in particular is from some of
the palace of death Egon nicaya and
number two it goes much the same as the
previous suit just more expensive and
then after it talks about the hindrances
being abandoned says seeing that these
five hindrances have been abandoned in
himself delight arises when he is
delighted bliss arises that's P P when his mind's
bliss arises that's P P when his mind's
blissful his body becomes tranquil
tranquil and body he feels happiness
being happy his mind becomes composed
there starts talking about be honest so
what kind of delight and bliss and
happiness are we referring to here
because it seems to me that perhaps it's
not what we necessarily think of when we
think Mitchell II think of those terms
yeah that's because most most often
those terms are inseparable from
sensuality the central joy learner
account of gaining everything seeing
things hearing things tasting things
touching things smelling things
and this is community opposite direction
of life so that's why by recognizing the
extent of sensuality the extent of that
contextual perceptual pull and because
it's a pool means you're kind of
enslaved to it so that's why by
recognizing it by fully discerning it
you you free yourself from it and that's
that's why the Buddha would say though
somebody is free from those hindrances
from that kind of pool he experienced
joy because you really feel like you're
that free now oh there is no more burden
pressuring you or dragging or pulling
you in that sort of threatening manner
which means you're free from it which
then means you're free from the entire
sphere scope of things that you used to
have to do on account of sensuality just
because you were a victim you were a
subject to that displeasing amount of
pool in the background of your mind so
so naturally then being free from that
kind of burden that kind of pressure it
feels like relief
so that relief isn't it's a joyous thing
and there's relief results in calmness
it's same things clearly cuz you relieve
now you don't have anything to worry
about
how about when it's mentions like the
body being tranquil like how do we think
about that in a non sensual way of like
getting massage well no that's still
sensually that's what I'm saying how do
we think about it a non sensual way
right well it means the the tranquility
that comes out of freedom from
hindrances that relief is felt in the
body so in that sense the body
strengthen the body is calm the body is
Pleasant and that pretty much describing
of the pleasure that were described know
the first jhana like just to the right
amounts are not spilling out of your
senses but not denying the mind so
they're just left alone there and the
Buddha gave the simile what was the
simile yeah that's it but by adding
water to it and then you get the right
consistency it's not too much water not
too little water and you can get that
not by sort of measuring the father but
basically by knowing what too much and
too little is so in the sense for for
you for you for your body you know the
extent of central involvement and then
you know the extent of non involvement
in to that extent so you don't need to
then keep the knot you don't need to go
further and deny the body more than that
you've restrained it the mind has been
the - surmounted the hindrances and now
these senses elected ISM there is no
intent there is no attitude there is no
action that it's at the time present
that is founded in the senses towards
the sense objects they're left alone
just for what they are
which means they are pressure-free and
and relieved of a burden of the pool of
the sense objects but you won't get
there if you've been trying to deny them
either because you can't indulge them
but you can't deny them in the same
manner because either way you choose to
do you're gonna end up being involved
overly involved or unduly involved with
them which means it's either too much
water or too little water which means
there is still pressure either negative
or positive but the pressure is still
there
so we established that there's a so to
speak gradual path gradual training to
gradual path gradual training to
establishing the mind that composing the
mind
it's sometimes said that one enters
let's say jhana the really any kind of
establishment of Samadhi kind of in a
natural way like you just do keep seeing
the well restrain and then these things
arise naturally so to speak is that the
case here we just we wait for things to
arise they do well if by natural you
mean Oh automatically no not necessarily
you need to you need to know well you
need to understand the nature of
establishment of mind you need to
understand the nature of right composure
he can't just happen to you
it can't just happen to you or if
something happens to you it's not the
compulsion because you haven't been
composing it so yes there is a there is
a whole set of prerequisites which you
must develop and maintain but then also
knowing that it's about the background
of the particularly arisen experience
the general nature behind it that's what
you're supposed to discern it without
making it a foreground without overly
attending it without ignoring it without
understanding it either and that's
something that you need to know and if
you know that's how you can compose it
then eventually through that practice it
will not necessarily automatically
result in it although even if you if you
have really perfected the sense
restraint and wakefulness and
mindfulness inevitably you will start
looking in that direction because you're
already significantly withdrawn from the
particular from the full of the
particular sense context but yes it's
not it's not guaranteed it would be good
if there is some instruction you might
get a hint of it or something but then
you would actually have to willingly
turn there and go their way that's
actually that's here what the Buddha
done he would when he was trying to
figure out what could be the way of
developing the mind fully properly he
remembered that kind of Pleasant
peaceful burden free pressure free
experience he had under the tree
still young and I thought well what if I
go there and by going that way we
actually the studio developed it and so
another one of the similar lines was
when the Buddha was encouraging Mohammed
Alana to develop jhanas and in the
Buddha left
and Mawlana said under tree and then he
said first jhana first general what is
first jhana and it started contemplating
the factors of the first jhana started
basically reflecting upon the
description of the first jhana did the
Buddha gay and then by understanding
what there was he developed there is no
delay or discrepancy between
understanding and establishment
establishing you mind that's why the
world would praise the Janus in
themselves as well because even without
a right view you've got to develop a lot
of understanding in regard to the nature
and the basic characteristics of the
universal aspects of your experience so
the say a person without a right view
develops the janna's they're gonna need
very little instruction to become
another hand because they have already
done most of the work through that
correct establishment of the mind
another concept that comes up quite
often in the traditional literature
regarding concentration is the nimitta
terms like sign broadly speaking they
discussed that in terms of generally
like a light that one has arise when
they have the stage of concentration and
then elated and so decided more things like
elated and so decided more things like
that I think we've spoken about and of
why it doesn't really seem to make much
sense in the context of composing the
mind already
well even even in the sutras in general
nimita is always mean signs and tokens
of the experience like oh what's the
significance of this and exactly so you
can say all the significance is disliked
them but that's not see that's just
another perception a more general
perception and more ambiguous perception
Nima ties the signs and tokens behind
the particular perceptions yeah you
perceive those signs a talk is but only
that in direct manner if you directly
look at directly look at it I mean
something else is the significance of
your direct look and again we don't have
to go further than that similarly that
suited that you read with the
thoroughbred horse he doesn't get
absorbed with a golden limit out of the
of the color of the hay now he looks at
what's the significance of me being fed
this hay as in what are gonna trigger
what is the the horse trainer gonna ask
me to do because of this what's the
background that's the limiter so exactly
developing discernment of the background
means already you are you're not being
pulled by the particular things in your
in Europe in a foreground so to speak so
developing that kind of discernment of
the background means developing the
Namita in that particular regard to that
experience so it's kind of a crude example just
so it's kind of a crude example just
because it's a very kind of baked term
like a sign and token those things let's
say we have a like a literal sign like
stop sign right a nimitta is not like
the actual science science what is the
meaning of stop don't pass this line
exactly that's the negative but most
people would think nimita is the sign
it's the actual physical board that says
stop but it isn't that steer is an
object that you're perceiving that has
the limiter of certain implication of
don't go past this point so that's the
limiter anonymity is always in that
background so particular things in your
experience that you threw through your
perception point obviously at various
backgrounds and that's why the signs and
tokens of the mind because the mind is
always on that background even the sign
of the mind
chipton emitted it's like a almost like
a prerequisite for the right view for
sort of party means basically you need
to know the direction of the development
of mind in order to begin to develop
your mind
that's what Chetan Amit is a
prerequisite for Sam Aditi
and here's here's that the suitor that
kind of goes into that that's from the
book of sixes of being gooder and Akaya
see - 68
it says because for a big coup who
delights and company who takes a
pleasure and company who engages in the
light and company who delights in a
crowd so on so forth crowd that he
should enjoy being alone and secluded is
not a possibility not enjoying love
being alone in secluded that he should
pick up the sign of the mind it's not a
possibility not picking up the sign of
mine patients also write views on a
possibility not having themselves right
view that he should so so right
composure is not a possibility not
having to celebrate composure that
should abandon the center is not a
possibility not having abandoned the fetters that he
not having abandoned the fetters that he
should realize Nirvana is not a
possibility
it's kind of self-explanatory based on
well based on all the previous things
I've said
just exactly that the perpendicular
development is not one two three four
five but by being withdrawn from the
people by being restrained from the
Census you start finding peace in
solitude but being in solitude you start
to see the beggining of your mind
clearer because you're not constantly
bombarded by the sense Pole as in by the
particular content by not being
bombarded by the sensible by being
properly established in that solitude
you start to discern the significance of
their background then the limiter of
that background the signs and tokens of
that background which is their mind and
that's how you develop the understanding
and that's how you begin to practice
right there is no correct Samadhi
without the right view as that suta and
many other suitors would often say and
that's another thing that people often
choose to ignore because they find
meditation help nobody says you should
stop trying to meditate but don't think
you know married you know how to
meditate rightly unless you have the
right view
here's another suit dealing
signs and tokens from the 47th Sunday to
Pacific dönitz some need to dance called the
dönitz some need to dance called the
cook it says suppose a foolish
inexperienced unskillful cook were to
present a king or royal minister various
portions of curries various flavors that
foolish inexperienced unstuff will cook
does not pick up the sign of his
master's preference today this crepe
cleveland master you reached for this
one it took a lot of this one he spoke
and prayed this one or this one or that
one and so on so forth
that foolish and experienced or scuffle
cook does not gain clothing wages or
gifts to what reason because in this way
foolish cook did not think of the sign
of master preference so to because some
foolish and experience and skill to be
COO dwells contemplating the body in the
body ardent we're mindful
displeasure in regards to the world
while he dwells contemplating the body
in the body whose mind did not become
concentrated or composed his defilements
are not abandoned he does not pick up
that sign and so on with the other three
sake batana
it seems here almost like intuition
where it's described in this simulator
yeah it means basically knowing what you
do knowing what you're doing this so you
don't know what you're doing in the
beginning but you're learning by seeing
the results of it by seeing the the
implications of it but seeing how it
effects things then after a while you
become skilled that cook becomes killed
he doesn't even have to think he knows
exactly how to please the king it was
exactly what he likes to eat on what day
is and after he's been eating this so
that why cuz she's been looking at it he
wasn't just looking at oh yeah this he
did it is that's it I'll just make this
or make that sometimes it's this
sometimes is that but in order to see
that you must stop being concerned and
absorbed only with what you see directly
with your perception you need to start
seeing things indirectly in that
background that are they're
simultaneously present with whatever
else you perceive it and the same goes
actually even contemplating body in the
body correctly it's already that when
you step into the background in regard
to your body that's how the body is
twice doubly present so to speak
background in regard to the particular
experience is the is the beggar of that
particular experience which means it's
inseparable from which means you can be
absorbed in the body or if you reflect
mindfully from body then you see body in
that body because you you create a
buffer zone by stepping back into their
general without looking at it in the
same direction so you leave okay there
is a body here and now there is you
mindful of yourself seated paying
attention to this particular
so that's body in the body it's not like
see the body further within the body
further within the body further within
the body because that's not even you
lost the sight of the initial body let
alone seeing the further bodies
so when it's one of saying here that the
unskilled Baku
he's trying to contemplate the body in
the body or feeling some feelings or
whatever yet he's still at the same time
he's not becoming composed he doesn't
pick up well actually when that
unskilled big fool it's actually
relatively skilled for them contemporary
practices of meditation he's at least
doing body in the body correctly the
Buddha didn't dispute that but then he
says that on account of that practice he
doesn't look further he doesn't see the
signs and the signs and the tokens of
that experience of mindful body in the
body because that's how you get to
understand it but initially he sees
correct his practice of building the
body ardent resolute to be drawn from
sensuality that he's doing that very
well what I'm saying is that most of the
the meditation approaches people take
today they don't even do that correctly
they focus on like imagine every body
within the further imagery well it's not
even a body anymore it becomes theories
and almost like like like abstract
notions that you perceive that you think
you're perceiving but in order to
perceive them in any shape of form that
you believe you can he will require you
to step outside of your experience so
while you're thinking perceiving it you
all you're doing is engaging in a view
that you are outside of your experience
as in seeing yourself in that impersonal
and independent of the five aggregates
and of what has arisen so that's I mean
that's not even seeing the body let
alone seeing the body in the body but
now you have to go further for somebody
who does learn how to do properly
composure based on mindfulness or body
within the body then he needs to start
looking at the background of that and
that's how it developed he develop signs
and tokens eating out of that experience
in the background of him doing
mindfulness of the body
well the significant tokens the signs
and tokens of the experience of being
mindful of body in the body that's not
something you can do that's something
that you can discern based on the
principles of this sermon that you've
been cultivating up to that point but if
you don't that's what Allah says the
foolish man but she didn't take it as
far as he couldn't shoot
I wanted to start explicitly discussing
jhana itself
is there any particular English
translation that is appropriate for
Jonah or if something really seemed to
sit well whatever you choose to
translate it with is going to require
lots of explanation because
well because all the views associated
with it so no translation will be
perfect well leaving untranslated it's
not perfect either because he needs to
be understood
that we at least establish it's like I
kind of end up referring to these
establishments of mine
I know it's it's it's a bit off but it's
not a concise terminology but maybe I
think about its if I'm in town with one
boy the opposite
we established previously that it's it's
it's it's a long line of composing the
mind yeah let's call them the first John
is the first composition somalis
composure practice of composure jana is
the composition
can there be some money that isn't
Jonathan yeah sure I mean Samadhi as in
Esther composure of your mind you can
you can compose it in regard to well
various approaches work very various
ways of looking at things but it's
really if your mind is developed a
sufficient extent then you can see the
extent of the first jhana of the second
jhana even if your practice is not
necessarily the practice of jhana
you might be doing other types of
mindfulness first John is is basically a
way of attending to certain aspects of
your experience with a developed mind
that's how you establish that's how you
compose that first jhana there is
outside of the central domain gone
quite secluded from sensual pleasures
secluded from unwholesome phenomena
with thinking and pondering and rapture
and happiness born seclusion he enters
into wells in the first jhana enters and
dwells
means he spends time in it
so we can go into discussing perhaps
each of these pairs of factors
first is secluded from sensual pleasures
so seclusion some some people say that
John and John uh you don't experience
the senses all that's why you're
secluded quite the opposite
you've surmounted the senses which means
they're very much the full extent of the
sense the main is right in front of you
and the reason why people can never be
aware of the full extent is because they
give in to the pull of the sense object
way too soon if you don't give in then
the positive object in the negative
sense the whole domain becomes what the
Sun and that's why the first John in
another suit to the Buddha said the
first jhana is a sale by the perceptions
of sensuality that's was trying to
undermine you first jhana it's basically
stepping back and seeing the whole
picture the whole nature of sensuality
senses and sense objects so those senses
still remain subjected to the pool of
the objects but you have surmounted them
which means you don't share that their
nature anymore you don't partake in it
you are not being pulled the senses
remain the senses and sense objects are
a natural indispensable counterbalance
they define each other they are
inseparable so you don't shut them down
you find a way out without interfering
with them without trying to deny them so
you leave them alone that's why what I
said just a few minutes before few
minutes ago is that you free yourself
from that sensuality quite secluded from
sensual pleasures by surmounting the
domain of the body being there this body
present right here because that's where
your senses are the body is the five
senses so if you establish like a mindfulness
so if you establish like a mindfulness
of the body and there you you you've
established like the condition for the
senses yeah it's the right direction to
go but you will know that you are that
you are outside of the central core when
you have experienced the relief from the
central pool which is undeniable but in
order to experience relief from the
central pole means you need to
understand and fully see the extent of
the central core now just replace it
with something else you think it's more
lofty to look at wholesome states of
claiming that all these results than in
craving for or against lust ill-will
delusion distraction distraction means
dependence on the variety of the content
boredom root in the same domain
so we're saying then that there's also
no craving regards to like any kind of
like putting crudely like mental
phenomenon yes there is no you're not trying to get
yes there is no you're not trying to get
rid of it either which is unwholesome
you're not trying to get rid of it
either because they like Austin Shorty's
bad I must get rid of it since Charlotte
is bad I must surmount it and learn how
to stop interfering with it because you
need to feel with it either by giving in
or trying to get rid of it
so that's exactly why the first jhana is
secluded from central present from
unwholesome States just included from it
but you are not trying to get rid of it
either you leave it alone because it's
not your problem and it's not your debt
it's not your pressure it's not your
your duty and your burden it means off
I'm relieved Chara here translator
Hey traditionally Tucker is like uh
conventions like initial strength of the
mind yes right commentarial definitions
doesn't matter the point is once you
have surmounted once you fully discerned
the extent of the body the extent of
sensuality and it's corresponding poem
once you disengage from it so to speak
what's left there is thinking and
pondering which means it's the same
thinking empowering
- sensuality so you're still engaged
yeah exactly but now there is nothing to
fear there is nothing to try to get rid
of because thinking and pondering was
never the problem he was thinking and
pondering about the senses about the
sense objects about the sense avoidance
about the sense lust and so on that was
the problem so he was lost a version
delusion they were the problem always
worth once once you live withdrawn from
it then thinking of wandering in stayed
that's exactly what what defines the
first jhana you've surmounted the body
and now what's right in front of you
usually what's right in front of people
is this is this body with the sense
options and sensible xand sense sense
engagement but through the discernment
of that background of that
simultaneously present background in
regard to your particular sense objects
you have developed this sermon of the
phenomena of the whole domain of the
body and then what's in front of you is
the thinking abundant not anymore the
counterpart of your senses which is
sense objects if you sort of turn Oh
will not turn away if you if you stop
being mindful of thinking pondering
correctly you are back onto the lower
level which is the level of sensuality
that's where somebody without the right
view somebody who hasn't understood the
nature of Assumption the nature of a
banana even if they have John is after
the giana they will go back to this and
Charlotte they could go back to
centrality but if once you will be wrong
pair them with the right view and right
understanding you won't be going back to
it even if you're not in the journal
enemy
rapture and pleasure yeah I think that
you mentioned before like the joy of
freedom yet the relief imagine your
pressure like a debt to pay back and you
know the debt collectors are there out
for you you don't know when they're
gonna pounce in comment and impound yo
your house and take away and whatever
imprison you so it's a big burden it's a
big stress to carry that's a definition
of a sensual world there's always
something pressuring and pulling you
going against you so you stepping
outside of the entire possibility of the
sensual world in Central Falls it's a
tremendous relief that's why first John
is more than enough to become an arahant
in origami
and the good mentions in some suitors
unlike pleasure of the senses there's
nothing lame worthy yeah yeah because
you can't crave you can't crave for for
more of a relief
you're either relieved of that which was
a problem oh you're not if you relieve
the from a problem is there's no problem
whatsoever it's a full relief so you
can't crave for more oh it's just
inconceivable that's why you can't crave
for more of the pleasure of the relief
actually the pleasure of the John if
people crave for it if people think of
you you can't have enough of it oh you
need more of it that's just another
sensuality that's the definition of
sensuality wanting more needing me
so in that context it may be gained a
little head but like in terms of like
the further John is that obviously they
become more was find more things it's
the refinement of the same principle so
as I said you have abandoned the
counterpart of of your sense objects of
your sense sense basis of your body
which is basically that the sense object
is the counterpart and what's in front
of you is the thinking and boundary but
then you can go further and abandon
thinking in pondering then what's in
front of you is the clarity of your
mindfulness and so on and that's why
often it would carry on into those other
kind of immaterial establishments by
following the same principles the boys
honors then oralism or what the
phenomenon of space the phenomenon of
consciousness the infinity of space zone
and then eventually the cessation of
perception of feeling and there is no
more than that but as I said where is
cessation perception of any audience at
first jhana the principle of the
establishment is the same that's where
the first yarn is sufficient for our
engine because it's upon the
understanding of the principle do you
develop the liberation and wisdom
company is sometimes simile is given
I'll give the readout the one that the
first jhana
it was from vegan acai at number two it
starts a thief reading it starts at the
first jhana formula and that says he
kills this very body with rapture Napa
is born seclusion he suffuses this very
body with it he makes the lock bury
bodies full of it
who pays the very body with it so there
is nothing in the entire body
it's not for beta class grab her
happiness course
and it gives simile of like
sprinkled some math powder eating it
with moisture and stuff so and it seems
to me this would be very easily
misconceive is like an energy slow
exercise sure sure how should we
understand it properly again you have to
come back to that notion of relief so
imagine you've been harassed by
something say a wild animal that you've
been chained to the animal and it was
just you were just dragged with it then
you were either basically at the mercy
of an animal or you have to fight it
back and constantly drag it and sort of
dig your heels and endure it and if you
don't know that the problem is not the
animal but you being bound up with it
because of that subjected to the things
that animal wants because of not knowing
that you don't know how to free yourself
from it in other words people might be
blaming what animal wants to get what
anyone wants to eat when he drags you
might be blaming the animal they don't
know how to leave the animal alone no do
they know how to step outside from the
the animal range but if you do then you
can literally have it sitting right in
front of you but you know you won't go
there with your hand you won't get
hooked again onto it and if you're not
hooked it won't do anything to you so
it's it's it's mindfulness of that
relief in regard to the extent to which
you neither indulge no deny no try to
get rid of so recognizing the right
amount discerning that's there another
suitable you gonna say the monk doesn't
attend the jhana because he does not
attend to the theme of the jhana
basically he does not attend to the
theme of the extent it
needs to develop of extent of not
completely ignoring but not completely
indulging I'd not trying to get rid of
but not pretending it's not there as
well so that's why in order to attend to
the theme of something you need to know
what that theme is you need to have a
hint you need to have signs and tokens
of that theme and the seemingly the were
to give is that calm the mounting car
that wants to go to the pastures that
hasn't been before and then steps on one
Rock but without sort of steadying
itself when it's regular he wants to
step on the other one and there falls in
between the two so Jana is not like a
combination of some practice Jana is the
right practice that's the come in there
is no combination to it the joy of John
is the joy of doing it so to speak in
that correct manner which is a manner of
non doing pretty much that's what you
can't pray for it you can crave only for
something that's a number you can pray
for something that has no gold in it so
the the goal of Jana is the doing the
theme of Jon not the result of John the
pleasure of John is the pleasure of
doing the John oh he pervades it like
this he pervades in like that he thinks
he ponders he withdraws he steadies it
that's where the pleasure comes from
usually people think I'll do this on
meditate the concentrate constant and
then I have experience and that's John
the combination of joy and whatever
light that's my John I know John is that
doing which means you can be doing the
Jannah without still getting the
pleasure of Jannah that's why your mind
hasn't been steadied in the jhana but
that doesn't mean you're not doing the
Jannah that's why again as I said before
you can do other practices they would
equal to the strength of the mind of the
Jannah but not steady your mind John
the pleasure John is the pleasure of
doing it which means people should stop
expecting the great the great kind of
tremendous fountain of joy pouring out
as ecstatic result of their
concentration practice but instead focus
on discerning and fully understanding
what the theme of jhana is which is a
theme of surmounting the central domain
and then to it and through doing it it's
going to become Pleasant doing and once
you become established upon that
pleasure and experience that relieved it
Oh viola engage like this ROM
established like this no matter one
horse who can enter me and that's just a
tremendous relief and that's what
pleasure John a pleasure of doing is
right
and then is there further there is
there's a second jhana is there further
isn't it there is a for John so it's
it's it it's it's very sort of it can be
a big obstacle for people
the ingrained assumption and I'm
speaking from my own experience the
expecting like Janice or whatever
Samadhi to result in this experience
they kind of overwhelms you but actually
it doesn't result in it
you build it and through building it
that's where your pleasure gets gets
experience and that's why you can't
crave through it because it's not
something that's given that you want
it's harder you doing - you don't do it
if you don't do it you can't have it so
you could seem consumable to even crave
it
so studying the mind in the theme of
jhana is the practice of jhana even if
there is no pleasure in regard to it yet
there is a practice of jhana he started
in jhana and he's studying his mind in
the jhana he's attending to the theme of
jhana rightly if that's developed to
sufficient degree to sufficient
repetition and diligence again that's
why we always place diligence as well
because it's not given then you will
recognize the that experience in itself
is the experience of their joy and
freedom from that freedom from pressure
freedom from pull that you haven't been
recognizing why because you haven't
fully discerned the theme of the jhana
the extent of it because that that the
whole point you live next to the
Wobblies the drags you left and right
but you don't recognize when they're
Beast is left alone by not recognizing
you don't know how to cultivate so you
keep interfering with it and you keep
paying the price
so someone has the idea like I'm
they don't understand exactly what I
want Jonna they should divorce that idea
from the almost natural expectation or I
want that great experience pleasure cuz
that's just another craving for pleasure
which is another craving for sensuality
that's why as the Buddha said most
people end up meditating with sensuality
so if somebody wants to jhana and you
should want jhana then somebody must
make all the effort to understand what
that jhana is phenol logically mindfully
to be seen for what it is the extent
because again the Buddha didn't say oh
the monk doesn't know what jhana is and
he falls between these two rocks same
like the car with the windows Rock sorry
he said the monk doesn't attend to the
theme of the jhana because not attending
this particular extent so not too much
not too little this is the theme by not
attending it he doesn't establish it
between he has it everybody has it but
nobody knows what it is that's why they
can't attend to it rightly and that's
why they expect it wrongly so to speak
so it's basically that you're saying
please correct me if I'm wrong
that it's like
but it's but it's a pleasure of
understanding a Giana is the pleasure of
the Jonah yeah sure once the mind has
recognized itself being established in
that Jonah that's already that pleasure
of that John yeah that makes sense it's
like if you don't know you're relieved
and you're not relieved that's why that
you cultivate the pleasure of John it's
not given to you to some practice of
some technique or something and then the
pleasure Jonah comes over if pleasure is
like that that's the pleasure you can
crave for and if you can pray for it
means it's not the pleasure of Jonah
because as the Buddha said those a
pleasure it's awesome because you can't
pray for it